[Kaspar]: You are listening to Clap to Collap on Collaboradio.org
[Kaspar]: as a part of Freie Radio's Berlin Brandenburg, streaming on fr-bb.org and collaboradio.org, transmitting on DAB Plus channel 7D in Berlin and channel 12D in Brandenburg.
[Kaspar]: In this radio show, sound artist Kasper König presents interviews and sound recordings from Colab, Technobiological Futures, a project by the artist-run Bio and Hacking Labs, hosted on Hectoria.org and sponsored by Prohevitia.
[Kaspar]: Listeners are invited into a global network of makers, exploring the collective motivations behind the work and the unique context of this collaborative lab culture.
[Kaspar]: The show is edited and produced between Zurich and the Emmental, so expect a few holes here and there, both in the sound and the narrative.
[Kaspar]: Alongside uncovering these collaborations, the episode dips into music and sound art made in the Daivo spirit.
[Kaspar]: Do it with others.
[Kaspar]: Kasper König himself, a sound artist, also shares his fascination with unexpected sounds and surprising discoveries from the workshop.
[Kaspar]: Enjoy!
[Kaspar]: So how are you?
[Kaspar]: I just wanted to chat some small talk and then we deep dive into these three questions that I prepared or that you maybe saw already.
[Kaspar]: I'm curious to know also a bit more how you're doing just around the project and not just only the project wise.
[Kaspar]: Yeah, so much to talk about many issues.
[Kaspar]: So my question would be for you.
[Bora]: Who are you and what is the core of your lab?
[Bora]: Hi, my name is Bora Hong from South Korea.
[Bora]: and I live in Chiang Mai.
[Bora]: I'm an organizer for Parang Cafe Artist Day.
[Bora]: Parang is an artist residency and also the creative place that people gather and have a music and workshops and talk and networks, everything happening here in the garden and the studio.
[Bora]: And I'm also a curator for art and music program.
[Bora]: I'm also a designer.
[Bora]: And I'm running a venue called Long Sa Deng.
[Bora]: So Long Sa Deng is a kind of a theater, but it's also not really a former theater.
[Bora]: It's more like a bar.
[Bora]: but we have a beautiful floor so we can have various independent artists do a show together and then unusually like you know when I meet artists I can feel like oh I'm gonna connect this person to this person so we organize a show
[Bora]: And sometimes it's dancers with a sound artist or sometimes noise artists with classical musicians, sometimes jazz musicians with traditional dancers.
[Bora]: So it's all very fusion mixed experimental shows, performance going on there.
[Bora]: And yeah, so I'm doing many things and I'm like a third country person here.
[Bora]: I'm not Thai.
[Bora]: I'm not European.
[Bora]: I'm not, you know, Western.
[Bora]: I'm Korean.
[Bora]: So it's kind of advantages to connect to everyone like in the middle or sometimes it's just totally independent outsider.
[Bora]: So yeah, it's nice.
[Bora]: May I ask if you're referring when you say Korea to North Korea or South Korea?
[Bora]: South Korea.
[Bora]: Yeah, you see, there's a difference.
[Bora]: I would say, I would say South Korea is a luxurious, very, very first-world country, actually.
[Bora]: Yeah.
[Bora]: But you perceive it as a third-world country?
[Bora]: So, I mean, like, not economically.
[Bora]: I mean, like, the position itself, like, yeah.
[Bora]: I think here in Thailand, they call it Pharang.
[Bora]: Pharang is a Western, more like white people.
[Bora]: And then Thai, it's like Thai people.
[Bora]: and there is another people like just whatever tourist.
[Bora]: That's all.
[Bora]: Thank you.
[Bora]: That's for the first question.
[Bora]: Yes.
[Bora]: And we have two more to go.
[Bora]: But maybe one of the second question is related to the first question.
[Bora]: So I'm very interested in what is growing best in your lab.
[Bora]: So Collapse is basically the idea of all these laboratories.
[Bora]: But I see your venue is in exactly that laboratory of transdisciplinary arts coming together and you're matching these artists together.
[Bora]: I think it's a beautiful thing.
[Bora]: But what is it that you would say your share is the most or what is growing from your heart or what is the thing that you see emerges from all of your energy?
[Bora]: Yeah, so when I moved to Chiang Mai 2020
[Bora]: I accidentally became owner of the live music venue.
[Bora]: At the time I just started with the musicians and then have a live music every night and they have to coordinate in the show every night.
[Bora]: But my background is visual art and design.
[Bora]: So I kind of connected visual art and music together.
[Bora]: And it's just naturally happening.
[Bora]: Yeah, it depends on who I meet.
[Bora]: I could get a new idea what to do together.
[Bora]: And then that's why I thought I needed some place that artists come in to stay.
[Bora]: So I started artist residency.
[Bora]: I guess, yeah.
[Bora]: 2023 or four.
[Bora]: And then, yeah, at that time, I got no more technology-based artists, like a web founder of Tomorrow Lab.
[Bora]: And the young generations, they needed some space to do workshops or meetings, because there were just galleries or cafes.
[Bora]: But there was not many like studios or place that they can do whatever they want.
[Bora]: So it was nice that Wave introduced a mark.
[Bora]: Head Carrier co-founder and then Mark brought this idea of do it with others.
[Bora]: And then this is what exactly I always dreaming for.
[Bora]: Like, but I didn't know how to organize, how to program, how to connect people.
[Bora]: But Mark has a, you know, interesting experiences and history, long-term projects.
[Bora]: And so I learned a lot from Mark, but
[Bora]: as a curator or as a program organizer, I'm more always like, sorry, like, I always more like observer.
[Bora]: I was not really into the process of creating some art project or research.
[Bora]: I was more like mama to take care of everybody.
[Bora]: and then so this lab of course we've got funding and then
[Bora]: we had a small collapse, we have a big collapse, we have a long-term or short-term, and these laboratories, you know, things happening accidentally, mainly, even though we make a plan, like, oh, let's invite these artists, let's invite these guests, let's collaborate with this organization or this country.
[Bora]: We plan, but
[Bora]: many things like happening accidentally or unintentionally.
[Bora]: So this is kind of interesting, but it's also quite risky how we can go deeper under the lab, how we can make something meaningful within this short lab program.
[Bora]: So this Arai Korab, for example, we have some artists to stay more than a month, which is good, like it's a long term.
[Bora]: But in the same time, they ask me, like, what do you want to see or what do you expect from us to do?
[Bora]: And I was like, yeah, this is a networking.
[Bora]: This is like a sharing knowledge.
[Bora]: of each other it's not about making results it's not about making documentation it's not about making exhibition you know we we care about results but we care about more process and then this is kind of pros and cons like everyone kind of lost but also in same time have a freedom
[Bora]: So, yeah, in the future, I feel like the planning is very important, but during the residence program, how to communicate each other, to do things together, you know, set up the schedules, set up the meetings, set up the, you know, dinner or more communication we needed, I think, yeah.
[Bora]: And it's a right answer.
[Bora]: I don't know.
[Bora]: I'm just listening.
[Bora]: I'm very happy whatever you tell about what is emerging.
[Bora]: Because the growing, you told it already in the beginning, very beautifully about the music and the visual art.
[Bora]: You make yourself and then that they merge together.
[Bora]: And then the mark comes in and there's a bigger plan of how to make longer stays and more interaction and with the use.
[Bora]: I think this is the things that people also like to listen to.
[Bora]: to have actually an image of a snowball effect or a butterfly effect you know that is that is why I see my interest at least like how can I support that and this is part of it by making the radio show
[Marc]: Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries Carries
[Marc]: Come on, come on, come on, come on!
[Marc]: Bacteria in the tooth.
[Marc]: Bacteria in the teeth.
[Marc]: Oh
[Kaspar]: Clap to Collab.
[Kaspar]: It's a radio show that documents the beautiful network Collab, Technobiological Futures project initiated by Mark Dissier that we just heard in the earlier part of the show.
[Kaspar]: And actually we're going to continue to listen to an interview with.
[Bora]: Hi, my name is Bora Hong from South Korea.
[Bora]: So basically I would love to ask you the third question, which is basically also on that same level of how you would love to grow on or what is the future of your what we call this techno biological futures right in our application.
[Bora]: Yeah.
[Bora]: Because we need this word to kind of open the mind on also sustainability or on this, how are we going to stay on earth without polluting it all the time.
[Bora]: And I wonder, what do you see there?
[Bora]: Or what would you wish for yourself?
[Bora]: Would you have another?
[Bora]: But fill it in for you.
[Bora]: What is your future in that sense of growth?
[Bora]: It's okay.
[Bora]: It's actually very interesting because how the things changing nowadays are really fast, and then how many new AI programs appear, how many news, what happened in the world, how things change, how new technologies come up.
[Bora]: it's it's not easy to follow and digest and then as an artist or curator when I see the young generation there is no like a boundaries or like you know major title like oh I'm a graphic designer oh I'm a sound artist or I'm a
[Bora]: interior designer.
[Bora]: This thing is not going to be existing.
[Bora]: When I see our core artists, we just invited some artists that actually have many different backgrounds.
[Bora]: Some of them are doing media art, sound jobs, or hackers, or DIY artists, and many different projects or professions they have.
[Bora]: And then, you know, like when they arrived in Chiang Mai, we realized that most of them actually do sound jobs, and the media,
[Bora]: uh they are like DJs and musicians so we kind of created a show listen to the sound like ambient and its payment and improvised and then this thing just happening because of they have their own skills and then we cannot
[Bora]: define what kind of artists to you.
[Bora]: Of course, there are some traditional artists, like I'm sorry, painters, sculptures, but also the media and materials are changing, you know, so many bio-materials now, and designers, they're new materials.
[Bora]: So this kind of lab for me, especially the collectives, I feel like it's a new type of education.
[Bora]: It's a new type of school.
[Bora]: Nobody call us school, but actually it's perfect school because you know that when you go to the
[Bora]: There is a curriculum you have to achieve a certain degree but the lab or collectives activities you have to find your way to learn and then also teach and
[Bora]: This now I want to see the future.
[Bora]: If I do more lab, I would love to focus on more educational process than the drawing.
[Bora]: Hey, we are the artists, we do this.
[Bora]: I think this lab for me is very like, very nice test or our collab is
[Bora]: very good model for the future.
[Bora]: Yeah.
Oh!
[Bora]: you
[Kaspar]: This is an impression of the art space barang in Chiang Mai led by Boda Hong.
[Kaspar]: So if you are wondering what music and sound pieces in between are played in the show, it's basically part of the archive that I'm running on my own work.
[Kaspar]: Bart Lee, of course, concerts from the collab and all kind of participational concerts.
[Kaspar]: You want to tell us first the first question?
[Kaspar]: Who are you and what's the core of your lab?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So my name is Shi Wei Jie.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I'm from Taiwan.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I started being as a media artist since after 2000, I think.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But maybe I consider myself more like a maker.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: My training is not art.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: My training is interactive design.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Only until lately, I started my interest for series to really understand what is art.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yeah, I'm never into art industry.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I'm kind of always outside of the system.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So that's why I think that's why I connected to Hectoria.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But not just Hectoria.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I mean, anyway, I kind of learned everything from these kind of camps around the world.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So it's like a hacker camp.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I started after my graduation, I just found this e-textile summer camp.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I found a lot of B-textile artists there in France.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So that's how I learned how to work with flexible circuits, combining fashion and circuits.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I got a lot of passion and also knowledge there.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I just keep traveling every year just to visit this camp.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: And then I made another camp in Taiwan.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: And that one, I connect two cultures, like the Itex Tao people, and the local Taiwan indigenous Ataio communities.
Mm-hmm.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: you
[Shi Wei Chieh]: if you are wondering what you're listening to this is Clap to Collab on Collab Radio and we are actually transmitting from Zurich where we are part of the Freie Radius Berlin Brandenburg and we are streaming on FL-PP.org and of course on CollabRadio.org
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I'm an artist and then I do a little bit organizing and traveling, visit camps.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I think that's my labs.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: And until now I met Mark and then we visited many more camps later.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: The camps are your lab?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: The camp is a global society.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: What's the camps or the lab?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yeah, yeah to the camps as labs.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yeah
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I think this is, and they are always temporal, nomadic, international.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So that influenced my skills.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I made another thing like a mobile.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Like this is a laser projector for printing, for dyeing a fabric by lithography.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But everything is small so I can put it in my suitcase so I can travel around.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I'm also developing another solar cell DIY project and that is capable for
[Shi Wei Chieh]: You can DIY it with cheap kitchen stuff.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Unconsciously, I gradually developed my skill to adapt to my trips.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I would say my lips are quite traveler's type.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Your suitcase is the lab?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: My suitcase.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Sometimes one of my friends said she was marking my suitcase.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: She said I'm a magician and I carried it around.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: and all my tours in the suitcase.
Ah, question.
[Adam]: Best growing things in the lab are embryos, human embryos, DNA, cupcakes, streams, new human bodies.
[Adam]: We're working best at tissue culture or organ culture or incubation and alteration of
[Adam]: embryonic goo germ cells sperm eggs all of these grow really well even full germ babies sometimes mutant babies grow really well in my lab
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yeah, but now not so much anymore.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I still travel a lot, but not after this March.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: What grows best in your lab?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Right now is... Well, before... Before, I really love this project, like this laser diet, cyanotype project, but this is a bit old.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I can show you around.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Because I'm interested in dyeing.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So this is, it's a innovative way to dye, but it's not really actually dyeing.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: It's a photoemulsion and resography.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: and then I move on to this dye sensitize the solar cell and then you need to you need to bake it in an oven but you can also bake I mean you need you can produce your solar cell in your lab and you can
[Shi Wei Chieh]: develop it with cheap devices and we need to cook it, one step is we need to cook it and then you can sinter the semiconductor layer but I also use this smaller heat plate and also you can use kitchen stove when I'm traveling I use kitchen stove and then once you finish the
[Shi Wei Chieh]: The baking, you soak it into the dye.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Like here.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Like you color your stained glass.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: A bit dangerous but I'm trained well.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Great.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Can you describe it to the listeners what you just picked out?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: This is a conductive glass coated with semiconductor layers, which is your two electrodes of the solar cells.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So once you made these two electrodes, sintered and dyed, and then you can assemble them as one complete cell.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: And I like it because you can screen print it.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: You can dye it, you can color it, so it's just painting.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Everything you need is conventional DIY tools.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Ideally you could do it everywhere.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: The glass is the battery and you can power the cell.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I wanted to make an electronics album.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Every time you walk, they are a mobile package album.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I think that growth is the best.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But I don't get our funding for this.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I apply the science funding.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I actually start up the research funding for this.
[Adam]: So what is the style possibility if we are engineering for something other than perfection?
[Adam]: If we include the rest of the art world since or before realism of the Enlightenment, like the humanism of Michelangelo, and actually look backwards and forwards in time from contemporary art and from
[Adam]: All of the human myths that are ignored in the name of the human being, the measure of all things, which is bullshit.
[Adam]: So, we try our best to make new life that has a style that is not been all.
[Adam]: I am Adam Zaretsky.
[Adam]: The core of my lab is wet and juicy.
[Adam]: Let's go!
Yeah.
... ... ...
you
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Sorry, that was my problem.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I didn't put down off the other apps.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I'm back there.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Oh, the video left.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Great.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yeah.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Can you see the screen?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yes.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I developed the LLM Wiki with
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Tamagotchi interface Tamagotchi is a Japanese game like you know you know
[Shi Wei Chieh]: okay so you can choose your architect or artist or popo maker or socialist or professor scientist drinker and and you put the question and then you can develop this question to a better more mature question by
[Shi Wei Chieh]: by interactive with this LIM Wiki.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Firstly, I collect all the Wiki pages from different communities.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So behind this interface is a obsidian vault.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So these are from three communities, Hectoria and
[Shi Wei Chieh]: COVA account and SGMP.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Yeah, it's all the data with only the title of the page and the notes and a short description.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I didn't fetch all the content from the website.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Then you build a relationship
[Shi Wei Chieh]: of each page in certain ways, then it becomes a knowledge database.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: What do you think is your technological future?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Is it the school, for instance, is this the new way of learning that we take all weekies and we work around there or do you think AI could be the school administrator or what is your future idea or what would you wish to have yourself?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So exactly this game.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So what you were seeing is an artificial, it's an AI based library.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But the process to design the relationship in it is kind of relates to the cognition philosophy.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So to me, this is the interesting part, because now you are not interact to the statistic library anymore.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: This synthetic brain respond to your AI agents.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So I think the next level is we need to figure out or we need to concern
[Shi Wei Chieh]: consider what is the mind, what is the awareness in the next step.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I think I can already see that because now you have so many AI tools and you can create a very tiny intelligence and that works really well and independent.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Music playing
[Shi Wei Chieh]: you
[Kaspar]: You have been listening to Clap to Collab, the second radio show on Collab Radio, about the networking project Technobiological Futures, brought to you by Kasper Koenig in collaboration with Hectoria.org, Ear.edication, which stands for Environmental Artistic Research and SGMK, Swiss Megatronic Art Society.
[Kaspar]: You are listening to the interview with Bora Hong from Parang in Chiang Mai and Jiu N. J. from Taiwan.
[Kaspar]: Music and sounds by Julia Hodl, Joeper Schneider and Kasper König.
[Kaspar]: Edited by me Kasper König.
[Kaspar]: The Carrier Song was recorded on the 28th of June at my dentist's grow-hiding in Zurich.
[Kaspar]: Echo recordings were made in the gas storage in Schaffhausen end of May.
[Kaspar]: During the opening and some of the beats were made during Corona times in the basement studio in Zurich.
[Kaspar]: Thank you for listening.
[Kaspar]: Tune in to Clap with Collab on Tuesday, 18th of August at 2 o'clock.
[Kaspar]: Collab Radio is part of Frey Radio's Berlin Brandenburg and we are transmitting on DAB Plus channel 7D in Berlin and channel 12D in Brandenburg.
[Kaspar]: you
[Kaspar]: I don't know.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I think we need to consider what is human bias, what is our, maybe we are not,
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I mean, maybe we are not we.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Maybe I think there will be a paradigm shifting about what is the definition of self.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: So to me, this is quite biological.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But I don't know why biological.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: But anyway, I really like the cognition philosophy and to talk about what is mine.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I think in the next level, if you want to talk about biological, I think eventually you will, what is the self?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Or what is the?
[Shi Wei Chieh]: mind.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: Keep me on the list for when everyone's coming.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: I want to be there to see them too.
[Shi Wei Chieh]: One more thing I can ask you right now.
[Kaspar]: It's very simple.
[Kaspar]: I call the show clap to collapse.
[Kaspar]: and it was just because I had no other idea at that moment yeah and I thought it was a fun fun thing to to work with and yesterday night I realized maybe it is actually a beautiful sonic icon yeah if everybody that likes to be part of the show can just clap one time and then I make
[Kaspar]: yeah later on an amazing applause with all these single claps so if you like just clap one time then i have that already i want to do more yeah okay yeah thank you sorry always late i'm always late
[Kaspar]: What is important when you think about shaping the future?
[Marc]: That's a difficult question.
[Marc]: My own personal future.
[Marc]: I'm in a phase in my life that somehow I'm not so young anymore.
[Marc]: In fact, I do hope to continue these kind of global and intercultural connections and kind of
[Marc]: hopefully continue and also that these connections can sustainably be kept alive.